A Guide to the Jon Dasu Longaker Papers, 1920-2002
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Jon Dasu Longaker Papers, 1929-2002 (bulk 1956-1997)
The Library of Virginia
41157
7.2 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Biographical Information
Jon Dasu Longaker was born in Switzerland on 5 January 1920 and lived in Germany and Italy until 1929 when his mother and stepfather moved the family to the United States. He attended grade school in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and high school in Salem, Virginia. Longaker earned an A.B. degree from the University of Pennsylvania in 1941. During World War II he served in the US Naval Reserve from 1942-1946. After the war Longaker earned a master's degree from Columbia University and from 1947-1952 he was Ph.D. candidate at Columbia University, but he never completed his dissertation. He came to Richmond, Virginia in 1952 as assistant curator at the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts. That same year Longaker was hired, part time, to teach art classes at Randolph-Macon College, before the term was over he was hired full time as a department of one, teaching art history, studio art, drama, and music appreciation courses. Over the next thirty-seven years, he would go from the only faculty member to Chairman of the department at his retirement in 1990. Longaker spent his career not only teaching art to college students, but to the public through his long association with the Richmond Times-Dispatch and Commonwealth Magazine. He was art critic for the Times-Dispatch from 1956-1964 and drama critic from 1965-1985. After his retirement, Longaker continued to teach art and other subjects at local universities and to community groups. He died 26 July 2002 after years of battling ALS.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1929-2002, of Jon Dasu Longaker of Ashland, Virginia, consisting of articles, art lectures and research notes, letters, newspaper clippings, newspaper columns, photographs, and theater programs. Collection also includes material related to Randolph-Macon College, where Longaker taught for thirty-seven years, a memoir he was writing, as well as draft chapters for a book on Islamic art that had long been a lecture and research interest.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Alumni--Randolph-Macon College, 1970-1981 and undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- America Theatre Critics Association (ATCA), August 1976-January 1982. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Applicant Resumes, 1976-1982 and undated. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Art and Music Notes--Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Art Courses--Randolph-Macon College, 1970-1980 and undated. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction--Draft Chapter "Painting--Early Manuscripts", undated. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction--Draft Chapter "Painting--Early Manuscripts, undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction--Draft Chapter "Painting, undated. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction--Draft Chapter "Painting" and Notes, undated. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction--Draft Chapter "Painting", undated. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction--Draft Chapter "Painting, undated. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction Draft Chapter "Secular Structures, undated. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Art in Islam: An Introduction--Draft Chapter "Secular Structures", undated. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Art in Islam: An Introdcution Draft Chapter "Tombs, Monasteries, and Madrassas, undated. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Art in Richmond" Newspaper Columns, 1956. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Barksdale Theatre--Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Barksdale Theatre Programs, 1956-1959. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Barksdale Theatre Programs, 1960-1967 and undated. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Barksdale Theatre Programs, 1970-1979. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Barksdale Theatre Programs, 1980-1983. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Barksdale Theatre Programs, 1993-1997. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Albert C. Barnes, 1938-1997 and undated. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Catalog--"American Painting 1962"--Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Catalog--"Seventh Mary Washington Annual Exhibition of Modern Art, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- College Materials, 1939-1953 and undated. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence--Personal--Navy, 10 May-2 November 1944. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence--Personal--Navy, 3 April 1945-16 July 1945. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence--Personal--Navy, 1 August 1945-10 December 1945 and undated. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence--Personal, 26 October 1953-5 December 1953 and undated. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence--Personal, 18 January 1954-28 May 1954. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence--Personal, 11 November 1934-1995. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence--Personal, undated [1953-1954]. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence--Personal, undated. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence--Personal--Cards and Postcards, 21 December 1952-3 October 1994 and undated. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence--Professional, 1950-1975 and undated. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence--Professional, 1983-1992. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence--Professional, 1993-1995 and undated. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Curriculum Vitae, 1971-1991 and undated. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Drawings, undated. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1934-1983 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1944-1980 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1947-1997 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1952-1985 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1952-1996 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1955-1982 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1956-1994 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1956-1993 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1956-1964 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1956 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1957-1962 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1957-1989 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1957-1989 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1957 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1958-1959 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1958-1977. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1960-1969 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1961 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1962-1963 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1962-1993 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1966-1987 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1968-1983 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1968-1983 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1972-1979 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1978-1992 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1978-1979 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1981-1984 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1983-1988. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Files--Miscellaneous, 1999 and undated. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Files--Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Fulbright Scholar Award Application, 1990-1991. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Gallery Promotions and Art Notes, 1971-1975 and undated. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Greek and Western Visual Art Notes, undated. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- High School Materials, 1934-1937 and undated. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Instructors' Class Roll, 1970-1987. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Islamic Art and the Arab World Notes, undated. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Islamic Art Research and Newspaper Clippings, 1990-1997 and undated. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Islamic Art and Culture Notes, 1984-1995 and undated. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Islamic Art Research, 1971 and undated. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Islamic Art Research Notes, undated. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Journal, undated. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Lectures, 1955-1991. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Lectures, 1966 and undated. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Lecture Notes--Miscellaneous, 1955-1991 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Lecture Notes--Miscellaneous, 1997-1998 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Lecture and Research Notes--American Art, 1975-1976 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Ancient Western Art, 1980 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Medieval, 1981-1992 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Miscellaneous, 1958-1982 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Miscellaneous, 1964-1990 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Miscellaneous, 1972-1980. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Miscellaneous, 1975 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Miscellaneous, 1978 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Miscellaneous, 1983-1991. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Leture and Research Notes--Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Modern Art, 1979 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Modern Art, undated. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Lecture and Research Notes--Renaissance to Modern, 1993 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Lecture and Research Notes--South America, undated. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Helen Dasu Longaker and John Mark Longaker, 1926-1960 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Lyde Longaker, 1941-1992 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Memoir Part 1--Draft and Notes, 1965 and undated. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Memoir Part 2--Draft and Notes, 1995. (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Memoir Part 3--"From Alps to Ashland", 1997. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Memoir Part 3--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Memoir Part 3--Draft and Notes, 1998. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Memoir Part 3--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes,. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, 1998. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, 1983-1997 and undated. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, 1999. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 11)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, undated. (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Memoir--Draft and Notes, 1953-1991. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Naval Training Materials, 1942-1945 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1957 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1960 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1958 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1960 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1961 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1962 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1965 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1966 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1966 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1970 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1967. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1969-1972 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1972 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1972-1973 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1974-1975 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1976-1980 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1977 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1980 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1981 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1983-1984. (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Clippings--Arts, 1958-1995 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Newspaper Clippings--Comics, undated. (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Newspaper Clippings--"Stage", 1979 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Newspaper Clippings--Theater Reviews, 1968. (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Official Legal Documents and Personal Summaries, 1929-2002. (Box 12, Folder 16)
- Opera, 1964-1972 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 17)
- Personal/Family Documents--Miscellaneous, 1941-1989 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Photographs, 1934-1941 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 19)
- Photographs--Longaker in West Germany, 1961. (Box 12, Folder 20)
- Photo Negatives, [1940's-1950's], undatded. (Box 12, Folder 21)
- Photo Negatives, undated. (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Printed Music, Lyrics, and Songbooks, 1981 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Randolph-Macon College, 1977-2002. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Randolph Macon College and the Liberal Arts: Heritage and Horizon, 1980. (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Randolph Macon Players and Ashland Village Theatre Programs, 1953-1958 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Roundabout Theatre Company (New York) Programs and Related Publications, 1976-1977 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Mary Scrupe Resume and Art Slides, 1989. (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Shearings from the Flock of Seasoned Citizens Volume 9, 1997-1998. (Box 13, Folder 8)
- The Shepherd's Center--Art History Classes, 1994-1998 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 9)
- The Shepherd's Center of Richmond, 1993-1998 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 10)
- The Shepherd's Center of Richmond--Writing Your LIfe's Story, 1991-1995. (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Shrine Mont Family Conferences, 1972-1997 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Shrine Mont Family Conferences, 1972-1997 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Songs--Handwritten Lyrics and Music, undated. (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Songs--Handwritten Lyrics and Musci, undated. (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Theatre and Music Programs and Publications, 1932-1997 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Theatre--Miscellaneous, 1955-1972 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Virginia Film Society Program/Newsletter, 1972-1979 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Visual Art Materials, 1952-1997 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Talks, 1953-1994 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 7)
- The Commonwealth: The Magazinee of Virginia Articles, 1967-1977 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 8)
- The Potboiler Art Magazine, 1960-1961. (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Virginia Museum Theatre Programs, 1955-1958. (Box 14, Folder 10)